<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from an ejected Member of the House of Commons, to Sir Jo: Evelyn: shewing, the constitution of that councell, and the influence it hath had on the present times, with a judgement of future events.</title>
            <author>Skutt, George.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E463_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203469</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863418</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863418</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E463[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from an ejected Member of the House of Commons, to Sir Jo: Evelyn: shewing, the constitution of that councell, and the influence it hath had on the present times, with a judgement of future events.</title>
                  <author>Skutt, George.</author>
                  <author>Evelyn, John, Sir, 1591-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated "G.S. [i.e. George Skutt] Aug. 16. 1648".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept 14".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons --  History, (17th century) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER FROM AN <hi>EJECTED MEMBER</hi> OF THE HOUSE of COMMONS, TO Sir <hi>JO: EVELYN: SHEWING,</hi> The Conſtitution of that Councell, and the Influence it hath had on the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Times, with a judgement of future Events.</p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:162224:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162224:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> LETTER TO Sir <hi>JOHN EVELYN,</hi> from an ejected MEMBER of the Commons Houſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am ſorry I am not in a capacity of retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one civility for another, being bound up by the unfortunate aſpect of my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to receive benefits rather then to give. Only I can ſay, I have committed your obligations to a faithfull memory and a gratefull heart, who will at all times diſcharge their Offices I am ſure, in paying you all juſt and due reſpects. But for your laſt diſcourſe, wherein you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to have me accept the proceedings of the Houſe of Commons for my Ejection, and acknowledge the right of my ſucceſſors place; I deſire to be excuſed, till I am convinced by the Reaſon of Arguments, and not fortune of the Times.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:162224:3"/>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe I doe not envie him his cuſhion, nor the State, Dignity, &amp; Degree of Memberſhip: which if I miſtake not, begins to want ſomething both of the intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſique and extrinſique value. And if my Arithmetick be good, the Houſes had no ſooner diſordered their whole Number, but they have ever ſince beene buſied in Fractions.</p>
            <p>But I need not read Lectures to the wiſe; you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member as well as I, and are a witneſſe to all the truth I know or can ſpeak; How the things of this preſent age, were begun with moſt exorbitant <hi>Opinion and Pride,</hi> carryed on with proportionable <hi>Injuſtice and Oppreſsion,</hi> and are like to end with equall <hi>Shame and Folly</hi> to the firſt Attempters.</p>
            <p>With what an aire of popularity was every man lifted up at the very firſt meeting? Flattering himſelf in the honour of being a publique Champion for the almoſt captiv'd liberty and intereſt of <hi>England:</hi> and of being a <hi>Member</hi> of that Parliament, which the People (who meaſure all things, not by what is fit and juſt, but by what themſelves deſire) already had in adoration. So that theſe men that could not govern themſelves by their particular vertue, no ſooner came to live in the hot aire of vulgar acclamations, but they grew half mad.</p>
            <p>An abſolute Calenture had ſeized on the head of the Body politique, which made them believe, they could do no buſineſſe but by precipices.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Speaker</hi> was ſo giddy with his vertiginous Office, that after a whole day ſpent in hearing and doing pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Affaires, he could ſeldome give account, you know, of what was ſaid or done. Which, I ſuppoſe, proceeded from the various qualifications and tempers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162224:3"/>of the <hi>Members:</hi> whereof ſome were wiſe men, but ſeemed not ſo, being ſuperſeded with acute prejudices and paſſions: Some ſeemed ſo and were not, ſeeking Fame rather then deſerving it: Others neither were nor ſeemed ſo, and yet had publique Faculty to uſe their incorrigible confidence of troubling the Houſe when they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>And though no man came to the Parliament but whom the Writ ſuppoſed both wiſe and valiant; yet that was to be underſtood favourably, for it appeared at laſt, that paſſions and feares had taken away the reputation of both.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain that theſe humours quite overthrew the State, Rule, and Order of a wiſe Councell. Doe you not remember how the Mornings were uſed to be paſſed away in long-winded declamations, brought thither elaborately compos'd, and read out of a hat perhaps, or behind a friend? And for the ſecond Scene, How about Noone (for ſo the match was made) came ſome Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from a County, City, Corporation, Myſtery, or Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation, and made humble deſires to have the ſame things done, which the <hi>Speech-makers</hi> had all the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning been debating of. Which alſo did not a little ſet forth the ſpeculative proſpect, and high wiſdome of the ſaid <hi>Members</hi> in publique Affaires. And it may be, after all this, the ſame <hi>Members</hi> receive Letters (of their own procuring) from their Country, City or Burrough, to give the thankes of their Truſtees to them, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their unwearied paines for the publique ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. So that by this time, the Gentlemen, ſwelling with opinion above the bounds of all ſhame or fear, ſent all their Orations to be Printed: whence came forth at any one time eight Speeches of Sir <hi>John Wray;</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:162224:4"/>ſoon after, nine Speeches more of Sir <hi>John Wray:</hi> all penn'd without wit and underſtanding; (and they muſt needs be ſo, for the Knight had none, and, where there is nothing to be had, the King loſes his right:) ſpoken without intelligible pronunciation and accent; and heard without attention; and yet ſent abroad to buſie the people with popular theames, and feed them with expectations of great effects. Whereas the wiſer ſort of men, thought it a great diſhonour to Parliaments, that theſe and other Speeches ſhould ever have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to the world, to give Strangers &amp; other Nations occaſion to think, what opinion they were to have of the great Aſſembly of Wiſe men in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt needs agree with me, that this liberty of <hi>Speech-making</hi> was <hi>Remora,</hi> if not the overthrow of all Parliamentary reſults; and made us many times more like perſons conveened in a Cock-pit, then a Councell: which cauſed a high reſentment in ſome temperate old <hi>Members:</hi> Among whom, (quoth one, ſtriking his hand on his breſt, in our ſight and hearing) I have been of all Parliaments ſince <hi>Duodecimo Jac.</hi> and never ſaw ſuch doings.</p>
            <p>Another cries out, that he had ſeen all the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and that of <hi>Oxford,</hi> where they were called <hi>Hornets,</hi> after they had been adjourned from <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> where they were but <hi>waſpes,</hi> all which were nothing to this. For whether it were the intemperate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of fame, or private opinion of parties, which often deceives men, and never more then at this time, or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall intereſts, or irregular zeal, or engagement in Faction and Deſigne, certain it is, that all concurred to uſe a liberty could be denyed to none of them: and they that held themſelves before almoſt undone for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162224:4"/>want of liberty, were now about to be undone with too much. The truth is, much talking is troubleſome in all companies, and in Councells dangerous; where all matters are to be handled with gravity and weight. But you remember well enough, that our long debates, which ſometimes held from morning till night, and then almoſt from night till morning agen, looked little better then great brawles: and when the people ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Gallant wiſe Members were very buſie, and took great paines, to ſit up late anights, making them good Lawes, they were then altogether by the ears per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, and drawing Swords, about the Candles. 'Tis as obſervable, how matters are not much mended, and that publique Affaires move ſtill by the like wild and prepoſterous conſultations: For, as when the reſt of the people lived in full peace, they were only then fighting and quarrelling in the Houſe of Commons; ſo now, when the Kingdome was put into open Warre, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent parties were every where acting Tragedies, on each other; when like wiſe patriots they ſhould be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the flames of publique diſcord, they are ſpending their time like young novices in Religion, and getting by heart a Catechiſme, which they have newly received from their reverſed Tutor the Synod.</p>
            <p>But popularity that bewitches all natures, not migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſupported with virtue and wiſdome, ſoon taught wiſe men, that there was no ſtop to be given to this careere of Speech-making, unleſſe the King ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the Parliament: which as the King had not done formerly without great temptation; ſo now to prevent it, the temptation being greater then ever, you know the arts were uſed; with all the deſired ſucceſſe that could be. And notwithſtanding His <hi>Majeſties</hi> great
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162224:5"/>alscrity in ſo important a matter, to conſent to the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of this Parliament, yet this ſecurity was ſo far from working off the clamour of the <hi>Members,</hi> that it raiſed the key higher, and from generall diſcourſes they deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded every day more and more to particulars.</p>
            <p>Happy was he that found out a Subject would tickle the attention of the Houſes, and could ſet it forth pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically. Doe you not remember how <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Layton</hi> out of the Gallery, dropt teares downe with his words? and did not <hi>Lilburne, Burton, Prin,</hi> and <hi>Baſtwick,</hi> find the like paſſionate Orators? and yet what effect did their glorious enlargements produce, but to let the world ſee the turbulent ſpirit of theſe men was habituall and not imputed; and juſtifie the proceedings of the late governours againſt them? And that 'twas no wonder they fell out with the King, His Privy Councell, and the Biſhops; when now being all at liberty, they could not agree among themſelves. For <hi>Prin</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>State-Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Baſtwick</hi> an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall; Burton</hi> an <hi>Independent,</hi> and <hi>Lylburne</hi> a <hi>Leveller;</hi> and all of them acording to the intereſt of their ſeverall cauſes, did not only write and raile at one another, and at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Members</hi> of the Houſes and the Army, but at the whole Army and Parliament it ſelf.</p>
            <p>It was ſtrange to ſee the cheapneſſe of your Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and what a facile ear was given to all Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Calumnies; as if the Parliament had been called only to hear Informations, or receive Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I paſſe by the Triumph was made over many great Perſonages in their loud Impeachments of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, &amp; the great labour was had to prove them. Some of which were ſold afterwards for money, and others to this day lie by the walls unregarded, and forgotten.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162224:5"/>And thoſe that did periſh by their Accuſations, ſuffered more, I doubt, to ſatisfie the pride and greatneſſe of the Accuſers then the merit of their Accuſations. And when the wits and underſtandings of men failed, their revenge &amp; malice bore up the undertaking; for when the whole Houſe was gravell'd, &amp; knew not how to proceed in the Tryall of the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> M. <hi>Pym,</hi> you know, was fain to call up that ſtupendious Oracle of all Learning, SELDEN <hi>the Great,</hi> to help the infirmities of the <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and declare (to the forme of proceeding what had been the practice of former Ages in the like Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The matter reſted in the hearts of the Accuſers, and needed no aſſiſtances. As appeared ſufficiently upon the cloſing up the evidence at the Bar by M. <hi>Glyn,</hi> who ranging all his matter to the beſt order and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage he could to charge the Priſoner; ſeconded with a reſerve of his own aggravations, made ſuch a tedious, unſatisfactory, impertinent clamour, that of thoſe Lords who ſhould have heard him, ſome fell aſleep, others lay along tired, all found out ſome diverſion for their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented thoughts, repreſenting to them, the fatality of that great Peer's life before them; which they could not ſave, becauſe they ſaw the Commons would not.</p>
            <p>You muſt needs remember upon all occaſions, how nice &amp; tender they were ever of their Orders and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; holding them ſuperiour to all Laws and Rules whatſoever. It was a State ſacriledge to invade either of them. Whence it came to paſſe, that their own, and their ſervants perſons were free from all Legall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in all cauſes and Courts. And one <hi>Benſon</hi> a <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> man, thought the vertue of <hi>Member-ſhip</hi> ſo great,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162224:6"/>that he extended it to protect <hi>fourſcore</hi> perſons, none of his ſervants, at one time, for which alſo he received 20s. a piece: and I beleeve, the firſt example that ever was, of protecting a Rape by Priviledge of Parliament, was, in the perſon of that godly and faithfull Member to the Cauſe, whom they called <hi>Prince Griffith.</hi> I know there hath been ſomething done of late to remit protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and humble the power of Parliaments; which ſignifies no more but this, that in a time, when peoples mindes were in a tumultuary diſcraſie, ready to break the reines of Government, and ſome temper was fit to be adminiſtred; nothing was thought more popular nor apt to court the People into their Obedience, then to offer them to lay down this <hi>Spell of Priviledge,</hi> which, while they were about them, no creditor could do them hurt.</p>
            <p>What opinion the Houſe of Commons had of the Lords was ſeen every day, for it appeared all along they were made ſervile to the deſignes of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>And in truth, it were too much trouble to put you in minde how often, and how tamely they have ſuffered themſelves to be baffled out of as much right and reaſon, as would have ſerved for noble advantages to have raiſed their loſt honours to their Ancient greatneſſe and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. And in caſe (as of late it hath happened) that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions and Addreſſes were made to the Houſes, which exactly ſuited not with the ſence and ſucceſſe of their preſent deſignes: Doe but obſerve what the different receptions of them were; with how much more ſecret State and Dignity the anſwers were delivered from the Lower Houſe; who, when they dare, will be ſure to reprehend; and when they dare not, their anſwers ſhall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162224:6"/>be made up of ſuch ſupercilious ſentences, as ſhall ſignifie nothing; or ſome cold opinion of the action, and leave the Petitioners rather to ſtudy out their own duty, then expect redreſſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis an athletick labour to put you in minde of every thing: But you may ſuppoſe, that when ſo many were got together, that could think themſelves, any thing: that there was no Power, nor Juriſdiction, nor Rule, but they were that: it was no hard matter for them to make a tranſition from the power to the execution, and fall to acting any thing.</p>
            <p>Hence it came to paſſe, that <hi>Treaſon</hi> againſt the King, and <hi>Sacriledge</hi> againſt the Church were become popular Topicks. The firſt was upheld under the pretences of reſtoring the Crown to a ſtability of Greatneſſe and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty; and the other covered with the title of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. But theſe appearing at laſt with their diſguiſes off, diſcovered only the power of ſome active &amp; ſubtle Members working out different deſignes through the borrowed reſemblances of Juſtice and vertue.</p>
            <p>You need not be remembred with what notorious partiality and favour thoſe Cauſes were received, which belonged to perſons of Parliamentary affections; and how the others were either put off with terrour, or ſo long tired with delaies, (for which there were a hundred known tricks among <hi>Committee-men,</hi> and after a while grew no more to be any of the ſecrets of their Courts) that they were undone with hoping to be relieved; and had nothing left them but the memory of their innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and right; which was now referred over to the day of Judgement for a hearing: where no art of a <hi>Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> or power of a worthy <hi>Member,</hi> can foreſtall the action, or pervert the juſt judgement.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:162224:7"/>
            <p>It well beſeemed indeed the wiſdome of the Houſe, wandring in a wilderneſſe of various matters without end or order, to take care that all <hi>Committees</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning private matters ſhould be nulled: and yet when <hi>fourſcore Committees</hi> were reduced at one time, M. <hi>Hollis</hi> had the favour to have that <hi>Committee</hi> continued, which concerned a ſuit of his own in the Court of Wards, (as I remember) becauſe he was then a leading <hi>Member:</hi> which was noted at that time a groſſe partiality. But this, you know, was the common uſe of all Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary references; for no <hi>Committee</hi> was ſo ſoon made, as it was immediately converted to ſerve the revenge, envie, avarice, or other corrupt humours and paſſions of the Authors: So that to commit a buſineſſe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied no more, for the moſt part, but to give the <hi>Members</hi> advantages of working their own, or their friends buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and deſignes with ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>But your partiality to friends was not more conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, then to your reputed enemies was your indiſtinct ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour &amp; impartiality: for, as if you had ſtoically held all men to be equall ſinners, you did indeed make them all equal in oppreſſion; the King, with his meaneſt Subjects. For you have oppreſſed all alike in their conſciences, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, honours, dignities &amp; fames: in their wives, children, kindred, friends and ſervants: in their lives, liberties, perſons, goods, and properties. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that both of us have often heard ſome of theſe things called Tyranny in the King and others: and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thence taken to puniſh the Actors with the acts. Which kind of Juſtice how you will avoid, your ſelves having been Judges in the caſe already, I cannot ſee. 'Twill be no plea to ſay, you were fooles or knaves, though all the world think you are both. The beſt you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162224:7"/>can ſay for your ſelves is, that you were mad; &amp; that you may prove perhaps, by ſome of your late actions. For what elſe was the voting of your <hi>Members,</hi> in and out ſo often? Your Voting men into Priſon for High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Voting them out agen for you know not what. Your Voting there ſhall be <hi>no more Addreſſes to the King,</hi> and then Voting that there ſhall. A temper ſomething like to that of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. who advanced men in a good hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour he knew not why, and ruined them agen preſently in another he knew not for what. But theſe reſolutions of yours, are anſwered abroad with the like diſcourſes: Some ſaying that you are, and other that you are not a <hi>Free Parliament:</hi> Some ſaying that many of you are, and others that you are not <hi>Members</hi> duly elected. Which, how true it is I examine not, but I have heard, that the vertue of the <hi>Army</hi> hath been at ſeverall elections, to keep the peace, as they call it: to ſay no more.</p>
            <p>Many there are, who think you a mad company, <hi>in ſenſu compoſito,</hi> as well as <hi>diviſo:</hi> You have two <hi>Speakers,</hi> a <hi>white Speaker</hi> &amp; a <hi>Black Speaker:</hi> But the <hi>white Speaker</hi> like the white witch, ſoon unravelled all the ſpels of the <hi>black Speaker,</hi> when he once appeared with his <hi>Familiar</hi> in both Houſes. Which was alſo, ſuch a deep diſſembled ceremony, that no man but ſaw through it; and did beleeve with reaſon, that the <hi>Members</hi> brought his Excellency to the Parliament, and not he them. I am ſorry to hear, that you were one that ran upon this Errand: though I know many Presbyterians did it, whom temporall reſpects prevailed with, to be of the ſure ſide. Yet, who would have thought that any worldly profit or preferment, could have moved old <hi>Rous,</hi> a man in matters of Religion and Conſcience,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162224:8"/>alwayes eſteemed ſevere and reſolute; now in his old age when he can keep nothing long, to runne away from his imbibed Principles and perſwaſions, to be continued yet a little longer <hi>Provoſt of Eaton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, Sir, God will have an account of theſe things; and will let you ſee, that all thoſe calamities that attend great alterations in States, are better prevented with wiſdome, then puniſhed with juſtice; and the day will come when the memory of your own Votes ſhall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you more then a thouſand deaths.</p>
            <p>For, if whatſoever comfort ſhall remaine of our elap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed humane life, will conſiſt in the charity which we exerciſed living, and in that Piety, Juſtice, and firme Faith, for which it pleaſed the infinite mercy of God in Chriſt to accept of us and receive us; what ſhall we think of you, whoſe actions have tended to baniſh all Charity quite out of Chriſtian Churches &amp; Societies; to diſſolve in all families and neereſt relations, the Bonds of naturall Piety; to ſuperſede in all Courts the execution of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Juſtice; and to fruſtrate the vertue and power of all Religion towards God and Man, under pretences of higher perfection?</p>
            <p>A ſtate as dangerous as that of the old Phariſees, whoſe ſtrictneſſe far exceeded yours; and yet, becauſe they juſtified themſelves in their ſins, and buſying themſelves in ſmall popular duties, omitted the weightier matters of the Law, Judgement, Mercy, and Faith, what woes unchangeable and eternall doth our Saviour Chriſt fulminate againſt their affected hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie?</p>
            <p>Now, if you are not guilty 'tis well. But, how you have kept your Faith with Heaven in your Proteſtations, Vowes, and Covenants?</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:162224:8"/>
            <p>How you have kept your Faith the with King, in your Oathes of Allegeance, and your many Declarations to make him glorious and great?</p>
            <p>How you have kept your Faith with the Church in matters of Reformation? After you had declared, <hi>die Sabbati,</hi> 9 Aprilis 1642. <hi>That you intend a due and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Reformation of the Government, and Lyturgie of the Church, &amp; to take away nothing in the one or the other, but what ſhall be evill, and juſtly offenſive, or at leaſt unneceſſary and burdenſome. — And to eſtabliſh Learned and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Miniſters, with a good and ſufficient maintenance throughout the whole Kingdome, wherein many dark corners are miſerably deſtitute of the meanes of Salvation, and many poore Miniſters want neceſſary proviſion.</hi> As if to take away nothing in the one and the other, <hi>but what ſhall be evill, and juſtly offenſive,</hi> ſignified, <hi>to take quite away, both the one and the other:</hi> and to eſtabliſh <hi>learned Miniſters with good maintenance in dark corners,</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>to put out Learned Miniſters, and put in young confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding dunces; divert the Church profits to your owne uſes, and make tenne dark corners for one that was before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How you have kept your Faith with the <hi>Scots</hi> in your Treaties, (made when you were in adverſity, and broke when you were out of it) and in the Solemne League and Covenant?</p>
            <p>How you have kept your Faith with the people, in ſecuring to them, their known Laws and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? And</p>
            <p>How you will keep your Faith with them in paying them all their monies agen? God knowes. And our own ſad experience in humane Affaires hath told us
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162224:9"/>now ſufficiently, that, <hi>Nulla fides pietaſque viris qui caſtra ſequuntur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I look upon you now as Souldiers, and your mercenaries wear not more iron then you doe about your hearts; where no precepts of vertue or Religion can make impreſſion. Which made you ſo great ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to peace and innocence, that you have not been ſatisfied with breaking your own Faith and Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but have made others break theirs too. As in the North &amp; Weſt parts of <hi>England,</hi> in the infancy of theſe troubles, when the Counties there, had agreed upon Articles between them, and thereto engaged their Faith to remaine Neutralls; you held it an odious reſolution, and cauſed thoſe of your Faction to break it, againſt the Lawes of Juſtice and Honour. All which, with too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of your Actions, have made the times ſo tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall and diſaſtrous, that the prudence of thoſe former Councellors of State ſeemes fully vindicated, who (miſtaken by the vulgar ſenſe to have done diſ-ſervice to the Common wealth) well judging of the temper of late Parliaments; put a ſtop to their dangerous effects by diſſolving them. And however it ſounds to the ear to wiſh for no <hi>Parliaments;</hi> yet it is hard to wiſh, what we are all bound to doe I think, that God would have removed far off from us this day of affliction, and not alſo to wiſh we had had no <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time, you will believe, I have not argued my ſelfe into a deſire of being amongſt you agen, or think my ſelfe, or any of my expulſed companions cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of the Honour of being of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> which is neither <hi>juſt, free,</hi> nor <hi>compos mentis;</hi> (though it have ſomtimes <hi>lucida intervalla,</hi> which happens when ſome moderate men are onely left in the Houſe:) And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162224:9"/>ſcandall you labour'd to raiſe upon us for deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our <hi>Truſt,</hi> as you call'd it, (when we fled from the guilt of your deſignes, and left you going about by fine arts and force to raiſe the Ball of diſſention betwixt the KING and His People) we know very well, that Game, if it began with <hi>Pym, Hampden, &amp;c.</hi> and was handed over to <hi>Hollis, Stapleton, &amp;c.</hi> is caught up now at laſt by <hi>Cromwell, Ireton,</hi> and their Complices: and whither it may be carried, God knows. But through all theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternative deſignes and variable intereſts, it cannot be ſaid, I hope, that nothing hath been done, but what the people at firſt entruſted you to doe. When it is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known, that even at this time, the people every where diſlike what you are now a doing: and are ready to pull you off thoſe Benches, did not the Army you keep up reſtrain them. And though it be a long time ſince you branded all thoſe who concurred not with you in your actions and deſignes, with the malevolent note of Malignants, yet now that all <hi>England</hi> is about to turn Malignant, with what pretences and arguments you will ſupport your undertakings we daily expect. If that of <hi>Salus Populi</hi> have any truth or reaſon in it; as your controverſal Writers for the <hi>cauſe</hi> have taken moſt exact paines to prove by diſcourſe, you muſt now prove it by your example, and yeild your ſelves a ſacrifice to the common good; that the Kingdome may be reſtored to the peace it groans after, and is only obſtructed by your obſtinacy and malice: for as long as you ſit together at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the people can neither be ſafe nor quiet. And truly, I have alwaies eſteemed it, a notable effect of Gods divine anger upon you, deſigning you to that juſt deſtruction God hath prepared for you, that, as the caſe ſtands, you did not <hi>all,</hi> before this time riſe &amp; run away.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:162224:10"/>
            <p>Whence the generall hate and deteſtation of your very Names and Perſons proceeds, you need not much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if you call to mind; Firſt, that imprudent and irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall demeanour of yours, towards all thoſe whom you had the fortune to reduce to your obedience. For among them who came in upon overtures of favour and candour, held forth in your Declarations (as many did, upon that Declaration of both Kingdomes of <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1643.) how were they received with neglect? looked on with contempt and ſcorne enough? and the favour ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, deluſively denied or detained; till your diſtracted <hi>Proſelites</hi> gnaſhed their teeth at their ſupine errour and folly of giving credit to your words and promiſes. And were not all thoſe that made Conditions upon Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Townes and Caſtles, like to have found little uſe and benefit of them, if the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Generall</hi> had not interpoſed to make them good, againſt the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and vindicative ſpirit of ſome amongſt you, whom no Reaſon nor Religion could rule againſt the ſwinge of their own violent wills? Contrary to the juſtice of all Contracts, humanity of fellow-ſubjects, and policy of all conquering Parties, and your own Intereſts; whom it concerned alwaies not to diſ-oblige, Country-men, friends, neighbours, and allies: but rather by love and mercy to work them over to receive with willingneſſe your dominion. For it is a ſure maxime, that <hi>Pateſtas humana radicatur in voluntatibus hominum.</hi> Where is then your power among a people that generally hate you? of whoſe affections while you are never ſure, ſo conſequently never of your own peace and ſafety. It is ſaid of <hi>Caeſar, Quâ vicit, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>os protegit ille man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And by that means the infortunity of the Roman Conqueſts became ſweetned with the prorection and ſecurity the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162224:10"/>Provinces received from the Roman Laws. For without queſtion, the greatneſſe of that Empire did owe as much to the heads of the <hi>Conſcript Fathers,</hi> as to the hearts of the <hi>Praetorian Souldiers.</hi> It being the manner alwaies of the Roman State after a new Conqueſt, to releaſe unto their new Subjects, half of that Tribute they had been wont to pay to their former Lords: which wrought ſo much upon their affections, that 'twas no mervail that <hi>Petellia</hi> a City of the <hi>Brutians</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> choſe rather to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all extremities of War, then forſake the Romans: and that too, after the Romans themſelves had confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they were unable to relieve them, and wiſh'd them to provide for their own ſafety, having been faithfull to the uttermoſt. And as this liberty of <hi>Rome,</hi> made her a moſt indulgent Mother to all her Citizens; ſo was it exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to other Cities, to let them have a taſt of her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Government; and in time became extended to thoſe far off, even to <hi>Tarſus</hi> in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> where Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was born, whence it was, that he claimed the priviledge of a Roman, <hi>Acts</hi> 22. Which examples have been ſo ill followed by you, that in ſtead thereof, you have injur'd all men; triumphing over your vanquiſhed foes with ſavage ferity, and over your Confederates, with falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, fraud, and treachery. For you may call to mind, if you pleaſe, your ſignall ingratitude to the <hi>Scots;</hi> to whom you owe firſt the very Being, and after that the Wel-being, nor onely of the Parliament, but of your ſelves, your Wifes, and Children: who in all humane reaſon had inevitably fallen under the power of the King's juſtice, had you not been reſcued from it by the aſſiſtance of your Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when you had with moſt pitiful moans and Meſſages called upon them for it. Then, your ingratitude to the <hi>City of London,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:162224:11"/>who was your <hi>Judas</hi> to carry the purſe for you; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out carrying the Parallel any further, unleſſe I ſhould ſay, that ye may perhaps in one thing be like our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt too; that as he was crucified, ſo ye may be all hanged.</p>
            <p>Theſe acts of high perſecution of your Enemies, and ſhameleſſe ingratitude and falſhood to your Friends, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders you equally hatefull to both. And if that of <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> be true <hi>—ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> enim libertas tutior ulla eſt, Quam domino ſervire bono:</hi> then are we become the greateſt Slaves in the world, becauſe we ſerve the worſt Maſters; whoſe arts have not been very admirable neither, ſince it did not require any great reach to carry on deſignes with that rule, of making great Engagements and Promiſes, and of never keeping any.</p>
            <p>But Ile be brief with you, and tell you; That there was a time when the name of <hi>Parliament</hi> was uſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timidate Kings and Princes, and the Great men of the earth; ſo now the time is comming, and is at the very dore, when the Name of a KING, (a Name in which <hi>there is power,</hi> ſaies <hi>Salomon</hi>) ſhall, by the revolution of Divine juſtice, intimidate all the lofty Titles of <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Chair-men, Committee-men,</hi> and whatſoever other Offices and Dignities are thereunto belonging.</p>
            <p>I know very well, the religious refuge you make to your famous Mother <hi>Shipton;</hi> from whoſe Oracles you think your ſelves ordain'd to depoſe, not only the King, but the Throne it ſelf, in the ſucceſſion of the Royall Line; becauſe ſhe hath ſaid, <hi>there ſhall be no more Kings and Queens of England:</hi> which is a truth the Devil hath told you enigmatically, to make you more ſure his own. For I am ready to believe as well as you, that there will be no more <hi>Kings nor Queens of England;</hi> and yet I doe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:162224:11"/>believe too, this Monarchy was never at that height it is now about to arrive to; by the bleſſing of God, on the preſent undertakings of men.</p>
            <p>For the union of the 2 Crowns of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo prudently fore-laid by <hi>Hen:</hi> 7. in the Marriage of His Daughter <hi>Margaret</hi> to <hi>James</hi> 4. King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> had no ſooner received the wiſht-for ſucceſſe in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our late Soveraigne King <hi>James;</hi> But both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes entred into a Treaty of rendring the Peace and union between them inviolable. And the wiſdome of the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> then em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for eſtabliſhing that union, conſidering that to advance the ſame, it would be profitable to remove all memorials of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union and ſeparation, endeavoured alſo that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon name of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> might be reciprocally taken up by both <hi>Nations.</hi> Which though it produced no other effect at that time then a Proclamation from K. <hi>James</hi> (as I remember) yet that ſhewed a true under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that wiſe Nation had, in improving the union to the utmoſt, both in name and intereſt: And to this day the ſame hath been proſecuted in the tranſactions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parliaments of both Kingdoms: and was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated by the Lord <hi>Lowden</hi> in a Speech at a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of both Houſes: and will no doubt have its juſt and reaſonable effect upon the ſetling of that Peace, both Kingdomes are now fighting for, againſt a generation of Vipers would eat out the Bowels of their Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with a malicious and obſtinate endleſſe Warre; to maintain the variable revolutions of their fancies, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and paſſions, which they call their <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and ſupport the neceſſity of their fortunes, which they call <hi>the Liberty and Property of all the Subjects of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:162224:12"/>I ſay, that you and I ſhall in a ſhort time live to ſee this Riddle of your <hi>Propheteſſe</hi> made good, againſt all the malice and power of your wicked ſenſe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: and theſe <hi>two Nations</hi> united into one common name of <hi>Great Britaine.</hi> And <hi>His Majeſties</hi> reſidence being drawn into the middle part of this hopefull Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, (which the world will then grow jealous of) may perhaps give a further iſſue to your <hi>reverend Sibylls</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, that <hi>Yorke ſhall be.</hi> Where His Majeſty and His Poſterity, no more uſing the ſtile <hi>of Kings and Queens of England,</hi> ſhall be ſaluted <hi>Kings and Queens of Great Britaine,</hi> to the worlds end: which God grant.</p>
            <p>Is it not time then, Sir, for you to look about you? and in ſtead of wiſhing me the Honour of being a <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> wiſh your ſelf the happineſſe of being none. Give me ſeriouſly in one breath, the juſt account of thoſe vaſt ſums you would willingly give, to have lived theſe laſt fix years at my little private <hi>Tuſculanum,</hi> reaping the joyes of innocent and peacefull houres: free from the diſorder and affranation of Tumults, prejudice of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and injuries of Warre. And tell me freely, or rather tell your own heart, what courſe of life you would not rather undertake, were you to begin again, then the unproſperous profeſſion of a Souldier: For beſide the envy and rage of men; the <hi>ſpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les, rapes, famines, ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the <hi>innocent, waſtings,</hi> and <hi>burnings,</hi> and other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries laid on the <hi>labouring man</hi> by you, have been ſo great, that were not the merc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of God infinite, it were in vain for any of you to hope for any portion of them, ſeeing the cruelties by you perm tied and committed have alſo been infinite. Your Votes for a <hi>Perſonall Treaty,</hi> can give us ſmall aſſurance of your affections to Peace, ſince you ſeem to be neceſſitated to them, by the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:162224:12"/>importunate deſires of the people; whom it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſuſpend, by giving them a cruſt, or ſomething to baite upon; while your ſelves acted all the while ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially and cunningly to render your own Councells ineffectuall: for to that purpoſe tended the neglect of your own Votes after they were made: your clogging them with <hi>preparatory Bills:</hi> your receiving <hi>Petitions,</hi> praying you to proceed in your own way: your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenancing others deſiring a Treaty; not to ſay, taking occaſion from thence perhaps, to murder and deſtroy the Petitioners themſelves: your limiting the place of Treaty to an <hi>Iſland,</hi> which is it ſelf but a larger Priſon: your attending the buſineſſe, with men of war; which invades the freedome of it. So that what you were aſhamed to deny in words, you profeſſe not to like in actions; and ſo long as Treaties and reconciliations are made up of the ſame ingredients as the late Warre, <hi>Feares and Jealouſies;</hi> 'tis not like that any other fruit ſhould be expected, no more then we can expect grapes from thornes. And whatſoever the pretences of ſome be, 'tis notoriouſly known, that thoſe who are eſteemed ſtars of the firſt magnitude in your Faction, by whoſe influence you act and move, have openly declared their Antipathy to all Treaties, and tenacious reſolutions to have the right of all controverted intereſts ended by the Sword; becauſe they very well know, the diſſolution their principles bring with them upon the preſent ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> and the novelty upon the whole world, will render them hopeleſſe of an eſtabliſhment by delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Counſell. And if the worſt ſhould come to paſſe, the ſucceſſe of your deſignes I mean, which God forbid, I doubt whether any acquiſitions could give reſt to the turbulent activity of ſome of your minds; or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:162224:13"/>whether there be any Kings under the Sun, whoſe means are anſwerable to ſome of your deſires.</p>
            <p>But to me it would ſeem a great wonder; did not the conſideration of the fraile ſtate and continuall fluctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſublunary things, hinder; from whence, I ſee the preſent ſtate of the war quite altered from the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the firſt undertakings, becauſe the worſer ſort of men perhaps by the variable ſucceſſion of time and accidents, are grown worſe then they intended to be; That about five years ſince, the <hi>Committee</hi> appointed to manage the Treaty at <hi>Oxford</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> 1642. ſhould be tied up to Treat onely with the KING, when He was free, and had many Noblemen and Privy Counſellours about Him, to have employed in that buſineſſe; And at this time, when He is a <hi>Priſoner</hi> and denied the acceſſe of His Servants and Friends, it ſhould be held ſo piam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and perilous and undertaking to Treat with Him alone, when there is no body elſe to doe it for Him.</p>
            <p>If the thing were unreaſonable, or diſadvantageous to you, yet many wonder, you ſhould run into a worſe hazard, by chuſing of two evils much the greater; in diſpleaſing one whole Kingdome; and probably the much greater part of another; in which, you yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to <hi>ſit and rule like Tyrants;</hi> thereby preparing the hearts of others to uſe you, juſt as you were uſing them ſo long as you had power to doe it. For all men are now grown full of hope, that the Hornes of your ſtrength and power are much ſhorter: and as you grow leſſe able to offend, ſo much the more will your majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call offers of mercy and indemnity be contemned and derided. That <hi>Indemnity</hi> you ſent to the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi> ſhewed the weak and ſhallow ſtate of your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: For after a few <hi>Gentlemen</hi> had raiſed the <hi>County</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:162224:13"/>into <hi>Armes</hi> againſt you, you held forth your golden Scepter of <hi>Indemnity;</hi> which the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves accepted of, but not being able to lay down the <hi>Armes</hi> they had raiſed, went home to live in Peace, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Country to fight it out with the Parliament; which they have done to ſome purpoſe: whereby you are gull'd of <hi>your mercy</hi> and <hi>your honour</hi> both at once. To the incomparable merit of that gallant old Peere the <hi>Earle</hi> of NORWICH, who went out of SUSSEX into KENT to embarque himſelfe amongſt Strangers in the cauſe of Loyalty; where he aſſum'd the conduct of a buſineſſe as full of hazards, as the Sea is full of waves: and when the ſucceſſe of that undertaking fail'd, put over into another County at the <hi>Iſle of Dogs;</hi> where he was received by a curriſh generation of men, making ſuch effectuall oppoſition, with the advantages they had, that Sir <hi>William Compton</hi> was forced to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle for the Souldiers, that at ſuch a place within a miles march, they ſhould all ſurrender their <hi>Armes:</hi> whither being come, and finding their condition deſperate, they reſolutely refuſed to part with their Armes, and, in caſe they were denied, would force a paſſage: which having effected, the march'd to <hi>Bow Bridge;</hi> where they plac'd a Guard; while their painfull old Generall, ſent to <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> and next day rode thither himſelf alone, to underſtand the reſult of <hi>the Rendevouz</hi> there: who by the example of their newly arrived neighbours and friends, paſt ſo many hazards to come to them, and the encouragement of their gallant Country-man S<hi rend="sub">r</hi> 
               <hi>Charls Lucas,</hi> reſolved to joyn Bodies; and ſo march'd to <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that if <hi>Kent</hi> have not done the work alone, yet it hath given fire to the train, which is like to run through
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:162224:14"/>all <hi>England:</hi> and hath begun a work, will end in the greateſt happineſſe this Kingdome could ever expect, <hi>viz. To unſettle this Parliamentary Army</hi> which is, <hi>to ſettle Religion, Laws, and Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in ſpight of all your confidence in the arme of fleſh, you will find, your glory is ſetting; and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of your Armes changing; the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> being about to loſe, together with his 50001. <hi>per annum,</hi> all the honour Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> won; and the Predictions of your own Saint M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> to be fulfilling upon you, who before he died declared his revelations of your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching ruine. And therefore, as <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid to his Sons-in-Law, ſo ſay I to you, <hi>Up and get you out of this place, for the Lord will deſtroy this City,</hi> Gen. 19.14.</p>
            <p>Your condition ſeeming to me very deſperate; for as you have ordered the matter, what confederate States have you abroad to help you, and receive you? as once you had of the <hi>Scots,</hi> in the like neceſſity. Or if you had, what Ships have you to carry you thither? Are you not in a pound? and will not every Petty Conſtable be hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to catch you when you run away? your very faces will betray you, being complexionall <hi>Traytors,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> by elementall conſtitution: for who can look upon <hi>Corbet, Gourdon, Say, Scot, Armyne, Cromwell, Rainsbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, Heyman, Ireton, Holland, Weſtrowe, Boys, Vane's,</hi> Father and Son, <hi>Morley, Weaver, Martin</hi> (that rapſody of all villany, and legiſlative <hi>Priapus,</hi> who was ſent for from fortifying of <hi>Reading,</hi> without impeachment of High Treaſon; becauſe though he be not for the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in all things, yet if he be againſt the <hi>King</hi> in all things, he is an inſtrument, <hi>par negotiis</hi>) <hi>Wentworth, Hill, Bond, Aſhe, Rous, Hoyle, Pury, Strickland, Blakeſton, Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham, Allen, Harvy, Walton, Skippon, Ven, Liveſey,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:162224:14"/>Luke's,</hi> Father and Son, <hi>Vaſſell, Love, Prideaux,</hi> and the reſt of the Saturnine crew, and not preſently ſee ſtrange apparitions in their very Phiſnomy, of Churches over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, Towns flaming, Houſes plundring, Widowes crying out for their Husbands and Children, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans for their Moneys. I muſt tell you, <hi>Sir,</hi> your very face, though it be one of the beſt in the company, looks ſtrangely when you come abroad amongſt honeſt men.</p>
            <p>Some believe, God hath ſuffered this defection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, to produce ſome great good to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: For this ſtate, being to ſuffer a totall abolition of the Government Eccleſiaſticall ſo long exerciſed in it; and to admit the erection of another, with many altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and qualifications in matters Civill; upon which depended the good eſtate and happineſſe of great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men and families; beſides, the queſtions in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſet on foot and maintained plauſibly by very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and pious Doctors and Preachers, would probably have had no reſt, ſo long as all thoſe perſons whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendances and relations were alſo great, ſhould remain unſatisfied either in intereſt or conſcience. Which work how to effect, it ſeemed impoſſible in the eyes of man: and therefore Almighty God, by raiſing up a third ſort of people, teaching principles and doctrines deſtructive of all the politique forms maintained by the other two, hath begot an union betwixt the Royaliſt and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian: and engaged the <hi>Scots</hi> upon ſuch good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable offices to the <hi>King</hi> and His loyall Subjects, that whereas all the world, expected with hopes, a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt betwixt the two Nations about ſetling of their Church diſcipline in <hi>England:</hi> it is now like to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, <hi>aequo &amp; grato animo,</hi> and all matters candidly carried, to a laſting good underſtanding between both
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:162224:15"/>Nations: which God of his good mercy grant.</p>
            <p>That at laſt we may ſee an end of this devouring Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whereof you are the Head, and is directed by your Councels, and maintained over us by your commands and authority: whoſe ends, are without end; and vary according to the liberty they take of thinking. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of men that agree in one only reſolution, of undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome:</hi> and are made up of as many different opinions among themſelves, as muſt certainly ruine them, when they have ruin'd every body elſe. Such as God hath ſuffered to get together, that being now known, and caſt out of the Common-wealth, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may hereafter be ſecure, and the Government flouriſh. In order to which, we ſee every day ſtrange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, which in a ſhort time will evidence, I hope, to the ſetled world; That as <hi>Saul,</hi> travelling long and far, with little ſucceſſe, ſeeking <hi>Aſſes</hi> found a <hi>Kingdome:</hi> So you, to invert the <hi>Simile,</hi> having ſeven long years given chace to a <hi>King,</hi> and lifted up your ſelves in the high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and aſſurance you had of obtaining a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> found at laſt you were your ſelves but <hi>Aſſes.</hi> And ſo I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>(Not of the Houſe of Commons I thanke God, and therefore the more likely to be)</hi> Your faithful and humble Servant, G. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aug. 16. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
